Lewis, Nahum H.; Papers apap156
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Nahum H. Lewis Papers
1896-2003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap156
0.5 cubic ft.
The collection documents the Jewish community in New York's Capital Region and the creation of the Albany Jewish Community Center.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Nahum Lewis in January 2003.
Historical Note
Nahum H. Lewis was born in Albany, New York in 1917. Lewis received his bachelor's and master's degrees from the New York State College for Teachers in Albany, New York (now the University at Albany). Lewis belonged to a variety of civil boards and was an active member of the Albany Jewish Community Center. Lewis founded the Bearing Distributors Co. in Troy, New York in 1946, where he worked until his retirement in 1991. Lewis died on November 22, 2003 and was survived by his wife, children, and grandchildren.
Scope and Contents
An eclectic collection of personal papers of Mr. Nahum H. Lewis and his father, Abraham P. Lewis, that documents the Jewish community in New York's Capital Region and includes material from the Troy chapter of the Zionist Organization of America, the Troy Hebrew Credit Union, and correspondence regarding the establishment of the Albany Jewish Community Center and a 1991 exhibit produced by the Albany Institute of History and Art.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized chronologically. There are no series.
Rensselaer County, New York; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; Lewis, Nahum, H. (1917-2003); Albany Jewish Community Center (Albany, New York); Lewis, Abraham P., 1896-1963; Jews--United States--Genealogy; Correspondence; Newsclippings
- Marx Family, 1896; 1999; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- YMHA/YWHA, 1917-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Shofar, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Troy Hebrew Credit Union, 1947; 1967; 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- ZOA - Troy Chapter, 1950; 2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- JCC, 1954-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Times-Union, 1961 (Flat-file 1)
- Brandeis University, 1961; 1965; 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- A.P. (Abraham P.) Lewis Remembrance, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- The Jewish World, 1965; 1967; 1999-2000 (Flat-file 2)
- JCC, "A Look Back-A Step Forward", 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- JCC 75th Anniversary Paperweight, ca. 1990 (Artifact-box 1)
- Albany Institute, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Background Information for Archival Donation, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)